I didn't expect this war to last so long.
没想到这仗打了这么久
Does His Highness really plan to enter peace talks?
世子真的打算和谈了
Will there really be peace from now on?
你说这以后真的能和平吗
Why aren't we fighting?
为何不打
The Monument of Loyalty was just erected.
刚立下忠义碑
In the battle of Jiuzhang Plain,
九丈原一战
we clearly won.
明明是咱们赢了
Runheng?
润恒
Yuanji.
阿姊
Here they come.
来了 来了
They're here.
真的是
Young Lord Xiao.
萧世子
I hope you have been well
九丈原一别
since our parting at Jiuzhang Plain.
别来无恙啊
Eagle King, you have come a long way for the peace talks.
鹰王为和谈远道而来
It must have been a hard journey.
辛苦了
This is...
这位是
This is the current Regent of Southern Ye,
这是如今南邺监国
Prince Qi.
岐王殿下
Prince Qi?
岐王
Never heard of him.
没听说过
Northern Qin cavalry has fought Southern Ye for years.
我们北秦铁骑与南邺交手多年
We only know Young Lord Xiao.
只知萧世子
It's fine.
没事
After the peace talks,
和谈结束后
you will naturally come to know me.
鹰王自然认识孤
Please.
请
Hold on.
慢着
Northern Qin and Southern Ye have been at war for so many years.
我们北秦与南邺打了这么多年了
Since we are having peace talks now,
如今既然要和谈
we, Northern Qin, must also show
那我们北秦也要拿出
our sincerity for them.
和谈的诚意啊
I have specially prepared a gift
本王特地准备了一份礼物
for Southern Ye.
要送给南邺
23 years ago, we captured your Capital,
二十三年前我们大秦攻入上京
forcing the Southern Ye royal family to flee south to Jiankang.
逼得你们南邺宗室南渡剑慷
These are the royal descendants
这些都是当年
of Southern Ye who couldn't escape back then.
没跑了的南邺宗室子弟呀
For all these years, Qin
这么多年我大秦
has been feeding and providing for them well.
一直好吃好喝地养着他们
Since we are having peace talks,
如今要和谈
we're sending them back
便将他们送回
to reunite their family.
弥补天伦嘛
Wuyi, they are going too far.
无衣 他们欺人太甚
Northern Qin is also divided into pro-war and pro-peace factions.
北秦也分主战 主和两派
The young Emperor wants peace, but the Eagle King favors war.
小皇帝要谈 鹰王好战
With the Eagle King leading the delegation,
而鹰王为这次使团之首
the peace talks will definitely not be easy.
和谈定然没有那么容易
Young Lord Xiao.
萧世子
Your Highness, the Prince Qi.
岐王殿下
Can you see my sincerity?
可知本王诚意否啊
The Northern Qin people are going too far!
北秦人欺我太甚
Stop them!
拦住他们
Stop them! Hurry, stop them!
拦住他们 快拦住他们
This is too much!
欺人太甚
Humiliating our people!
辱我族人
Stop them!
拦住他们
Yuanji.
阿姊
You animals!
畜生
Eagle King.
鹰王
Please.
请
Stop them!
拦住他们
The Northern Qin barbarians
北秦蛮夷
humiliated our nation.
辱国之耻
No peace talks!
决不和谈
The Northern Qin barbarians
北秦蛮夷
humiliated our nation.
辱国之耻
No peace talks!
决不和谈
Come on.
来来来
Let's go.
走走走
My Lady.
女郎
This is Honglu Temple.
这里可是鸿胪寺
We should probably go back.
要不咱们还是回去吧
The Eagle King humiliated our royal family.
这鹰王折辱我朝宗室
This is outrageous!
简直是欺人太甚
Didn't you hear what Yan Yue just said?
你没听刚才偃月说
The students are filled with righteous indignation
学子们义愤填膺
and have completely surrounded the Honglu Temple,
把鸿胪寺围了个水泄不通
just waiting to charge in and hack down the Eagle King.
就等着进去砍了鹰王呢
Even Mao went there.
连阿茂都过去了
But Xiao Wuyi
可这萧无衣呢
keeps the Beifu soldiers confined to the camp,
把北府兵按在军营里
not letting any news leak out.
一丝风都不透
What "bloodthirsty Yama Xiao" are they talking about?
说什么杀人如麻的萧阎王
If something really happens,
这要真出事了
he'd only act tough around us.
他也就只会窝里横
So we must hurry in and help Mao.
所以咱们得赶快进去帮帮阿茂
We can't let him be bullied by the Eagle King.
千万不能让他被鹰王欺负了
This...
这个
What's wrong with your throat?
嗓子怎么了
You secretly take the fire thunderstone.
偷偷拿了引火雷
Do you want to go to the Honglu Temple and blow up the Eagle King?
是想去鸿胪寺把鹰王炸了吗
No, no.
没有 没有
I really didn't.
真没有
Stop. I'll tell you.
别别别 我说我说我说
I heard that the Eagle King coming for the peace talks
我听说这次来和谈的鹰王
has a Longque Blade.
有一把龙阙宝刀
I want to see it.
我想见识一下
I also want to see
我也想看看
how the legendary number one blade in the world
这传说中的天下第一刀
is forged.
究竟是怎么锻成的
Know yourself and your enemy, right?
知己知彼嘛
If only I could also forge
要是我也能锻造出来
such a world-renowned, peerless weapon.
这样名动天下的绝世兵器就好了
Do I look stupid and easy to fool?
我看着很蠢 很好骗吗
Really.
真的
If I can actually forge it,
我要是真的打造出来
I'll give the first one to you.
第一把我先送你
The peace talks concern the lifeblood of Ye.
和谈关乎大邺命脉
If you dare to mess around...
你若敢乱来
Forget it if you don't believe me.
你不信算了
So naggy.
这么啰唆
You might as well tie me to your belt.
把我挂你裤腰带上得了
Okay.
好
Why did you skip the front door
你有大门不走
and fly up here?
干吗飞上来
If you're worried, go see for yourself.
担心 就自己去看
The Northern Qin barbarians
北秦蛮夷
humiliated our nation.
辱国之耻
No peace talks!
决不和谈
This is Ye's territory.
这里是大邺国土
Northern Qin lost the war.
如今是他北秦打输了 打败了
They're the ones suing for peace now.
来求和谈
I don't believe he dares to kill people in the capital of Ye!
我就不信他敢在我大邺国都杀人
Move away!
让开
Yizhi.
易之
Your Highness Prince Qi.
岐王殿下
You're finally here.
你可来了
Northern Qin humiliated our royal family.
那北秦欺辱我朝宗室
We were extremely angry upon hearing this.
我等闻之十分愤怒
If this can be tolerated, what cannot be?
是可忍孰不可忍
If the Eagle King doesn't remove his crown and beg for forgiveness,
若鹰王不亲自脱冠请罪
we will never agree to these peace talks!
这和谈我等决不答应
We'll never agree!
决不答应
What is this commotion?
闹什么
Have you forgotten what your master taught you?
都忘了老师教什么了吗
Students should concentrate on their studies
学子潜心修学
and not discuss state affairs.
莫论国是
Regarding this matter,
此事
I will discuss with Young Lord Xiao to find a resolution.
我会和萧世子讨论出个说法
You all leave first.
你们先散了吧
Your Highness.
殿下
Even the current regent hosting the peace talks
就连主持和谈的当今监国
is acting so cowardly.
也如此怯懦
Those Northern Qin bastards
那北秦狗贼
have already walked all over us,
都已经欺负到头上来了
yet you still endure blindly.
还一味忍耐
Scholars neglect statecraft; warriors neglect warfare.
文不思政 武不思战
Ye is doomed.
我大邺亡矣
Nonsense!
胡说什么
Throw!
给我砸
No peace talks!
决不和谈
You said you came to see the blade.
还说是来看刀的
But we can't just stand here and watch.
那也不能就这么看着啊
Are you this cowardly on the battlefield, too?
你在战场上也这么㞞吗
How did you win your battles?
你那仗都怎么打赢的
Do you think fighting a war is just hacking at each other with blades?
你以为两军交战就是拿刀互砍吗
Let me tell you the first rule of the art of war.
那我教你兵法第一句
War is a matter of vital importance to the state.
兵者 国之大事
It is a matter of life and death, a road either to safety or to ruin.
死生之地 存亡之道
It must be thoroughly studied.
不可不察
Stop!
住手
Move away! Move away!
闪开 闪开
Young Lord Xiao said
萧世子说了
that peace talks are state policy
两国和谈乃是国策
and cannot be changed.
不容更改
Considering that you are young and hot-blooded,
念在尔等年轻气盛
and the future pillars of Ye,
是我大邺未来栋梁
you will be lightly punished today as a warning—
今日小惩大诫
20 strokes of the cane.
杖责二十
General Yan Yue,
偃月将军
this is inappropriate.
此事不妥
The students are acting out of patriotism.
学子们毕竟是爱国之心
It is exactly because His Highness considers their patriotism
世子正是顾念学子爱国之心
that they are only getting 20 strokes.
才只杖责二十
Under military law,
若以军规论
those who violate orders die.
违反军令者 死
Anyone else who misleads the public
若再有蛊惑人心
and disrupts the peace talks
破坏和谈者
will be executed without fail.
定斩不误
Hit!
打
What are you doing?
你们干什么 你们要干什么
How can you hit people?
你们怎么能打人呢
Let go of me! What are you doing?
放开我 你们干什么
Xiao Wuyi, this...
萧无衣 这
Xiao Wuyi, how dare you hit me?
萧无衣 你敢打我
Yizhi, save me!
易之 救我
He even dares to kill officials.
他连官员都敢杀
The Empress Dowager can't even deal with him.
太后都拿他没办法
Why wouldn't he?
他有什么不敢的
Your Highness,
殿下
His Highness asks you to return to the Eastern Palace
世子请您回东宫
to continue drafting the peace treaty.
继续草拟和谈条款
Leave matters here to him.
这里的事交给他
Please.
请
Execute the punishment one by one.
逐一行刑
Look,
看
isn't it solved?
这不就解决了吗
Hey.
不是
Is this the solution you figured out?
这就是你说的办法呀
Those are Mao's classmates and friends,
那些都是阿茂的同窗好友
and you just had them beaten?
你就这么给打了
Xiao Wuyi, are you that afraid of the Eagle King?
萧无衣 你就这么怕鹰王
I really misjudged you.
我真是看错你了
Young Lord Xiao, His Highness, the Eagle King, invites you.
萧世子 鹰王殿下有请
Xiao Wuyi!
萧无衣
H-How do I get down?
我 我怎么下去啊
If you still want to play with fire in the future,
若你今后还想继续玩火自焚
you must first learn how to run away.
得先学会逃跑
What about today?
那今天呢
Figure it out yourself.
自己想办法
Figure...
我自
You...
你这个人
I—
我
Speaking of mutton,
要说这羊肉啊
it's still the best on Northern Qin grasslands.
还是我们北秦草原上的好吃
It doesn't have any gamey smell.
没有一丝羊膻气
Your Highness, try it.
世子 你尝尝
Mu Lianyu,
穆连余
you don't want peace talks at all.
你根本就不想和谈
Your Highness tramples on the people's will like this.
世子如此践踏民心
Aren't you afraid that the commoners will hate the Beifu Army
就不怕百姓恨上北府兵
and you?
恨上你吗
The people's will can be used,
民心可用
but cannot be fully trusted.
却不可尽信
You went to great lengths to provoke today's public anger.
鹰王煞费苦心挑起今日之民意
You just hope that Ye will call off
不就是希望我大邺先开口
the peace talks first,
停了和谈
so you can answer to your little emperor
既能让你向你家小皇帝交差
without taking the blame.
又不必担罪责
I really didn't expect
本王还真的没想到
that the decisive Young Lord Xiao on the battlefield
战场上杀伐果断的萧世子
would be so forbearing off the battlefield.
在战场下还如此这般隐忍
It seems you're having a hard time in Jiankang.
看来你在剑慷的日子也不好过呀
The feeling is mutual.
彼此彼此
If it weren't for the heavy snow,
若非天降大雪
we wouldn't have lost
九丈原一仗
the battle at Jiuzhang Plain.
我们根本不会败
In terms of archery and horsemanship,
论射骑勇武
our Northern Qin is far superior to your Southern Ye.
我们北秦远胜于你们南邺
But you lost.
可你还是败了
Otherwise, I wouldn't be able to eat
否则我也不能在剑慷
Northern Qin's roasted mutton in Jiankang.
吃到北秦的炙羊肉
Mu Lianyu.
穆连余
Now your little emperor also wants peace talks.
如今是你家小皇帝也想和谈
That's why you are sitting here.
所以你才会坐在这里
Please stop your tricks.
请你收回你的手段
Don't try to anger me.
不要试图激怒我
I can bear
民心之怨
the people's anger.
我担得起
Today, I have finally seen
今日 本王总算看清了
your sincerity in the peace talks.
萧世子的和谈之诚心呢
The most difficult part of the peace talks
和谈之最难处
is the ownership of the three northern prefectures.
便是北境三州之地的归属
In that case,
那既然如此
why don't our countries
让咱两国当众比一场啊
compete in public to determine
论定三州之地的归属
their ownership?
如何
I wonder if Southern Ye dares to accept this challenge.
不知你们南邺是否敢应此战
How do we compete?
如何战
Very simple. Shoot the willow on horseback—
很简单 走马穿杨
a game of life and death.
生死局
Do you dare to accept?
你敢接吗
Shoot the willow on horseback.
走马穿杨
Each country will send three people and three horses,
两国各派三人三骑
with three arrows per person.
每人三箭
When all arrows are shot,
箭矢射尽之时
whichever country has more arrows left on the target
哪国的队伍留在箭靶上的箭多
gets the three northern prefectures.
北境三州之地就归属哪国
Your Majesty, the Empress Dowager, these three prefectures
太后 此三州之地
were originally the territory of Ye.
本就是我大邺的国土
It's the Qin people who have been invading us.
是秦人一直南下入侵我军民
How can we use such a child's play
怎可以此儿戏之法
to determine the ownership of our territory?
定国土归属
Young Lord Xiao, what do you think?
萧世子 你怎么看
He proposed this competition
他提出此战
simply because he doesn't want peace talks
无非就是不想和谈
and wants to force us to refuse.
想逼迫我们拒绝
Even if we agree,
就算是答应了
he just wants to use this competition to win back their pride.
他也想靠着此战赢回颜面
In that case,
既如此
we shall fight again
那就再战一场
and make him admit defeat.
让他输得心服口服
Can you guarantee a sure win, Your Highness?
世子保证一定能赢吗
Matters on the battlefield
战场之事
can never be guaranteed.
从无保证
Even you can't guarantee it.
连你也不能保证
If we win this battle,
此战若胜
we might finally hold our heads high.
我大邺或许扬眉吐气
But what if we lose?
可万一败了呢
Your Highness and the Beifu Army will be ruined.
世子和北府将身败名裂
The three northern prefectures will fall into the hands of the Qin.
北境三州将落入秦人之手
The advantage of our peace talks with Northern Qin
我国和北秦和谈的优势
will also be gone.
也将荡然无存
Have you considered this, Young Lord Xiao?
萧世子考虑过吗
If every battle were a sure win,
若每一战都是必胜之战
there would be no war in this world.
那这天下便没有战争了
Let us fight.
一战也好
Let the people and scholars
也让如今那些
who are criticizing me see
骂我的百姓和学子们都看看
that the peace talks I led
我萧无衣主持和谈
were for the future of Ye,
是为了大邺谋长远
not because I feared war.
而非怯战
I am willing to fight Northern Qin!
臣愿与北秦一战
Wuyi.
无衣
Northern Qin was founded on military might.
北秦以军武立国
Their people excel in archery and horsemanship.
最善骑射
Are you really confident?
你真的有把握吗
Yizhi, why not think about it the other way around?
易之不如反过来想
If Northern Qin loses even the horse archery
若北秦连他们最引以为傲的骑射
they are most proud of to us,
都输给了我们
and loses three prefectures because of it,
还因此输了三州之地
what will happen within Northern Qin?
北秦国内会如何
Their morale will plummet.
士气大减
But that's easier said than done.
可这谈何容易
In this archery competition,
这走马穿杨
arrows can not only shoot targets,
箭不仅可射靶
but also people and horses.
还可射人射马
In the arena,
演武场上
the Eagle King will definitely use lethal moves against you.
鹰王定会对你使出杀招的
Then let's see if he has
那也要看他穆连余
what it takes to take my life.
有没有本事要了我的命
Yizhi.
易之
I'm sorry about what happened
昨日鸿胪寺
at the Honglu Temple yesterday.
对不起
I had no choice.
我也是迫不得已
You don't need to say this to me.
你我之间不必言此
I believe in you, Wuyi.
我信你 无衣
But for the peace talks,
只是这次和谈
what is your bottom line?
你的底线究竟是什么
Time.
时间
Conditions are not important,
条件不重要
but the reform of the Beifu needs at least three years of peace.
但北府改制至少需要三年和平
I am confident that after the reform,
我有把握在改制之后
I can increase the Beifu Army's combat power by 80%.
将北府军战力提高八成
As long as I have time,
只要给我时间
the Northern Expedition will definitely succeed.
北伐必胜
So no matter what happens,
所以无论发生任何事
no matter what tricks the Eagle King
无论鹰王还有什么样的招数
has waiting for me,
等着我
I must make the peace talks a success.
我都必须要让这次和谈成功
Wuyi,
无衣啊
I really envy your boldness and determination.
我真羡慕你的豪气与决心
Ye can lose three prefectures,
大邺可失去三州
but we absolutely cannot lose you, Xiao Wuyi.
可绝对不能失去你萧无衣
Losing three prefectures is a temporary loss.
失三州 失一时
Losing Wuyi means losing the nation's destiny.
失无衣 失国运
In the arena,
在演武场上
you must be very careful.
你可一定要小心了
Li Yizhi,
李易之
since when did you become so good at flattering?
你什么时候变得这么会拍马屁了
I'm speaking from the bottom of my heart.
我这都是真心之言
You don't know how much I envy you
你不知道我有多羡慕你
for building your career with your own hands.
靠着自己双手建功立业
Wuyi.
无衣啊
Do you want me to stay?
你希望我留下来吗
Do you think I, Li Yizhi,
你觉得我李易之
am worthy of being the Crown Prince of Ye?
配做大邺的储君吗
I didn't expect you, Xiao Wuyi,
没想到也有你萧无衣
to be speechless.
说不出话的时候
Never mind. I was just asking.
罢了 我随便问问的
Don't take it seriously.
不必当真
Jiayu doesn't like the palace.
嘉鱼不喜欢宫廷
Even for her sake,
就算是为了她
I can't stay.
我也不能留下来
By the way,
对了
the hawthorn cakes she made last time
她上次做的山楂糕
tasted really good.
味道特别好
I am not used to the food in the palace.
我在宫中饮食不惯
I rely entirely on them to whet my appetite.
全靠它开胃
Could I trouble you
可否劳烦无衣兄
to ask her to make some more for me?
再托她帮我做一点
I got it.
知道了
Later, let's give all the medicinal herbs
一会儿我们把今日带来的药材
we brought today to them.
都送给他们吧
I'll go take a look over there.
我去那边看看
Master. Master. Master.
老师 老师 老师
I told you to study behind closed doors
为师让你们闭门读书
and not discuss state affairs.
莫论国是
What about you?
那你们呢
Did you even listen to me?
把为师的话听到哪里去了
Do not get involved in the peace talks.
和谈之事莫要掺和
I am getting old
为师年纪大了
and don't have many days left to protect you.
能护你们的日子不多了
Please don't
你们就莫要再
cause any more trouble blindly,
不知天高地厚地生事端了
okay?
行吗
Master.
老师
It's not that we are acting blindly.
并非学生不知天高地厚
The Northern Qin people have gone too far.
实在是那北秦人欺人太甚
We study the books of the sages.
我等读圣贤书
How could we just sit by and watch?
岂能坐视
Today's blood
今日之血
is not to cause trouble,
非为生事
but to wake the people.
乃为醒民
And Xiao Wuyi,
还有那萧无衣
as the commander of the Beifu Army,
身为北府统帅
to fear the enemy
为了和谈
and abandon the people like this just for peace talks
竟如此地畏敌弃民
is an absolute disgrace!
简直奇耻大辱
Exactly.
是啊
Enough.
好了
Has your mother sent you any messages?
你阿母可有给你消息
Shouldn't she be at home?
阿母不该在家吗
Yaoyao,
夭夭
I am your father.
我可是你阿父
You've never been good at lying.
我知道你从小就不会说谎
Your mother divorced me.
你阿母跟我和离
She wouldn't keep it from you.
她不会不告诉你的
She did leave a letter.
阿母的确留书相告
She said all these years,
她说这些年
trapped in Jiankang Palace and the Grand Tutor's Mansion,
被困在剑慷宫 太傅府
she was very unhappy.
她过得很不快乐
Now that I'm married,
如今我也嫁人了
she can finally follow her heart
她终于可以随心而为
and live the life she wants.
过她自己想要的日子
She also said
阿母也说了
the divorce is between you two.
和离是她与你的事情
She is still my mother,
她依然是我阿母
and you are still my father.
你也依然是我阿父
That's all she said.
阿母言尽于此
Even if I knew where she went,
就算我知道她去了哪里
I wouldn't tell you.
我也不可能告诉你
If there's nothing else,
阿父若无他事
I will leave now.
夭夭便回了
For this round of peace talks,
这次和谈
a Northern Qin official proposed
有北秦官员提出
to send a royal daughter to marry into Northern Qin.
要遣宗室女和亲北秦
Who do you think
夭夭认为如今
is the most suitable among the Jiankang royals now?
剑慷宗室谁最适合
Li Lejun.
李乐君
You want to send Lejun away for a political marriage?
你们要送乐君去和亲
It's not us.
不是我们
It's Xiao Wuyi.
是萧无衣
Looking at his current actions,
你看他如今的行事
you can tell he will definitely make sure the peace talks succeed,
就知道他一定会让和谈成功的
no matter what it takes.
无论代价是什么
Everyone knows the miserable and maddened state
那日在城门之外
of the Southern Ye royal clan
铁笼之中
inside the iron cage outside the city gates that day.
南邺宗室的惨状疯状人人皆知
You surely wouldn't want Princess Pingning to suffer such a disaster,
你定不会想让平宁县主遭此劫难
right?
对吧
If you want to protect her...
若你想护她
I
阿父我
can help.
倒是可以帮得上忙
What's the price?
代价呢
Father,
阿父
what do you want me to do for you?
你又想让我为你做什么
The peace talks may succeed,
和谈可以成
but Xiao Wuyi
但萧无衣
must lose.
必须输
Lose?
输
Coincidentally, the bone is injured.
好巧不巧的有些伤到了骨头
You must give him the medicine on time, as I said.
你一定要按我说的按时给他服药
Pei Runheng?
裴润恒
Wake up.
你醒醒 醒醒
Doctor.
郎中
Your Highness.
世子妃
Do you know him?
您认识他
He is badly injured.
这人伤得太重了
Doctor, come here.
郎中 快来快来
Wake up. Wake up.
你醒醒 醒醒
The noble clans are committing treason.
世家卖国
They are parasites of the state.
国之蠹虫
Runheng.
润恒
-Who is Runheng? -You—
谁是润恒 你
Go away.
走开
Don't touch me.
别碰我
Do you know that scholar?
阿姊认识那位学子
I mistook him for someone else.
是我认错人了
He looks a lot like an old friend of mine.
他与我从前的一位朋友长得很像
Runheng would never look at me
润恒不会用这样陌生
with such unfamiliarity and disgust.
又厌恶的眼光看我
Besides,
而且
I saw Runheng's body.
我是见过润恒尸首的
Mr. Runheng was your sweetheart?
润恒先生是阿姊的心上人
On the day of the Double Ninth Ceremony,
重阳大典那日
I saw the prayer tablet you wrote
我在祈福树上
on the prayer tree.
看到阿姊写的福牌了
That name was on it.
上面就是那个名字
But I didn't expect that he had already passed away.
只是我没想到他已经去了
The prayer tree on the Double Ninth Festival
重阳日的祈福树
is also called the Yin-Yang Tree.
也叫阴阳树
It was originally meant to commemorate friendship with the deceased.
本就是为了祭奠故人的友谊
What?
什么
Then Ruisheng also...
那蕊生阿姊也
So you married Xiao Wuyi
那阿姊是因为心上人已经不在了
because your sweetheart was gone?
所以才嫁给了萧无衣
It was because I was going to marry Xiao Wuyi
是因为我要嫁给萧无衣
I beg Your Majesty, Empress Dowager for mercy,
请太后开恩
that he was gone.
所以他才不在了
I'm already engaged.
元姬已有婚约
His Majesty has just ascended the throne,
陛下刚刚登基
and his position is still unstable.
根基不稳
And the Beifu Army needs provisions.
北府军又正好需要粮草
Now is a good time for the He family and the Xiao family
此时正是我何氏与萧氏
to form a marriage alliance.
联姻的好时机
If you weren't the only eligible in the clan,
若非族内女眷唯你适龄
I would never force you.
姑母决不逼你
Aunt.
姑母
And I made the most regrettable decision
我又做了此生
in my life.
最后悔的决定
What was it?
什么事情
I told my parents and the Empress Dowager
我告诉父母和太后
that I already had a sweetheart,
我已有心上人
letting them know about Runheng.
让他们知道了润恒的存在
Runheng was the son of the academy's headmaster
润恒是书院院长之子
and a distant relative of my mother's family.
与我母族有远亲
I thought my parents would help me.
我以为父母会帮我
But not long after,
结果没多久
what I received
我等来的
was actually the news of his death.
竟然是他的死讯
Later, I found out
后来我才查出
that the border military situation was urgent at that time,
当时边境军情告急
and the Beifu Army urgently needed the He family's provision of support.
北府急需何氏的粮草支援
Because I kept refusing to agree to the marriage,
因我迟迟不肯允婚
the forces of the Empress Dowager and the Heir
太后和世子的人马
had both gone to look for him.
都曾去找过他
So someone murdered your sweetheart?
所以是有人害了阿姊的心上人
It might be Xiao Wuyi?
可能是萧无衣干的
Or it might be the Empress Dowager.
也有可能是太后
But if Xiao Wuyi really did it,
可若真是萧无衣干的
don't you hate him?
阿姊 你不恨他吗
In that battle,
那一战
Xiao Wuyi won beautifully.
萧无衣赢得很漂亮
He completely recaptured
彻底夺回了
the Yushan Pass, which was lost for nearly 20 years,
失去近二十年的玉山关
and is my family's hometown.
是我何氏的故乡
Tens of thousands of people returned to their homeland.
数万百姓归于故土
You tell me, how am I supposed to hate him?
你说我该如何去恨
Since then, I told myself
从那之后 我便告诉自己
to stop investigating.
不要再查了
Even if it really was Xiao Wuyi,
就算真的是萧无衣
I would still be Heir's Consort.
我也依旧会当好这个世子妃
But that's all.
但也仅此而已
The Heir only cares
世子这个人
about his own goals.
从来只看重自己的目标
He doesn't care about anyone.
不会管任何人
Yes.
是啊
So he will definitely make the peace talks succeed,
所以他一定会让和谈成功的
no matter what the cost is.
无论付出什么代价
Lady Xie won't be staying in the manor for much longer.
谢娘子在王府也住不了多久了
Once the peace talks are over,
等和谈结束
she will leave with Prince Qi.
她就要和岐王离开
Your Highness's efforts are all in vain.
世子做这些 白花费工夫
Who told you I made them for Xie Jiayu?
谁跟你说我是给谢嘉鱼做的
Your Highness, is your appetite poor lately?
世子 您最近胃口不好吗
Why do you love eating hawthorn so much?
这么爱吃山楂
They are for Prince Qi.
给岐王的
He wants to eat
那人家要吃的是
the hawthorn cake made by Lady Xie.
谢娘子做的山楂糕
Yet you let me do it instead.
您让我代劳
Where is my brother?
我哥呢
Did he go to the racecourse to find me again?
还去马场找我吗
Yes, he went to the racecourse to find you again.
是 大公子又去马场找你了
He still wants to compete.
他还是想上场比试
You can't just keep dodging—
世子老这么躲着
it won't solve anything.
也不是个办法
Your Highness, the racecourse reported
世子 马场来报
that Lady Xie secretly replaced all the stirrups in the stable.
谢娘子偷偷将马棚的马镫都换了
The stirrup is so loose.
这马镫松成这样
Anyone riding it will fall off soon.
骑上去没多久就得摔
If His Highness gets injured,
世子若受伤
he won't be able to compete.
就上不了场了
Could it be
难不成
that Lady Xie was really persuaded by the Grand Tutor,
谢娘子真的被太傅说动
and is making a move against His Highness?
还是要向世子出手了
Anmin.
大哥
Don't.
不可
Young Master Yao, there's something wrong with the stirrups.
大公子 这马镫有问题
They were replaced.
被人换过
You can't use them.
您不可用
I replaced the stirrups.
是我换的马镫
Yao's left leg is seriously injured.
萧大哥左腿重伤
A standard stirrup does not suit his archery on horseback.
寻常的马镫不利于骑射
So I specially replaced them with more stable ones.
所以我专门换了更加稳固的
Then, after he goes to the battlefield,
保证让萧大哥上战场后
he will be no different from a normal person.
与常人无异
If you don't believe it,
你若是不信
let him try it.
让萧大哥试试就知道了
I asked Lady Xie for help.
是我请谢娘子帮忙的
Anmin, no.
大哥 不行
Are the stirrups not good enough,
是马镫不行
or am I, Xiao Yao, not good enough?
还是我萧尧不行
This is the warhorse that will accompany me in archery.
这是要随我走马穿杨的战马
Because of this,
正因如此
I have to try it.
我才要试一试
Over the years, I've never given up on horseback archery.
这些年我从来没有放弃骑射箭术
Nor have I forgotten that I am a soldier of the Beifu Army.
也从来没有忘记自己是北府兵
I never abandoned myself to despair.
我没有自暴自弃
If it's just upper body strength,
若只是比上半身功夫
I am second to none.
我不输任何人
If it's really as Lady Xie said,
若真如谢娘子所言
I will compete in this match.
这场比试 我要上场
It's no use hiding from me.
你躲我也没用
Impossible.
不可能
Xiao Wuyi, make a move.
萧无衣 出手啊
I don't need you to hold back.
我不需要你让
Test me yourself and see
能不能上场
if I'm fit to compete.
你我比比看
Now you won't even
你现在连动手
fight me?
都不肯同我动手了吗
Anmin.
大哥
Why won't you let me compete?
你凭什么不让我上场
I don't accept this!
我不服
This concerns the three northern prefectures.
事关北境三州
I can't take the risk.
我不能冒这个险
Say what you will,
说破天
you still don't trust me.
你还是不信任我
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
-I told you my horse can help. -You—
我说了我的马镫可以帮上忙的
I trust even less.
我更不信任
Xie Jiayu.
谢嘉鱼
I know you met Grand Tutor Xie in the clinic.
我知道你在医馆见了谢太傅
And I know what he talked to you about
知道他同你聊了些什么
and what deal he made with you.
交易了些什么
You had me spied on?
你派人监视我
Burn all the stirrups and saddles that Xie Jiayu replaced.
将谢嘉鱼换的马镫马鞍全都烧了
Escort Anmin back to the manor.
送大哥回府
Yes.
诺
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
萧无衣 你放开我
Xiao Wuyi!
萧无衣
Let go of me!
你放开我
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
萧无衣 放开我
Let me go!
放开我
Put me down!
你放我下来
My Lady!
女郎
-Xiao Wuyi. -My Lady!
萧无衣 女郎
Xiao Wuyi!
萧无衣
My Lady!
女郎
Get out.
出去
Save it.
憋回去
Stop acting.
别演
Then Xiao Wuyi,
那萧无衣
who are you trying to make an example of by using me?
你又是杀了我这只鸡给哪只猴看
You needn't put it that way.
你倒不必这般形容自己
You have been in the army for so many years.
你从军这么多年
Whether the stirrups I made
我做的马镫
are harmful or helpful—
究竟是害人的还是帮人的
you should know it very well.
你心里应该很清楚
Even if you don't know,
你就算不知道
you would know if you let Yao try.
让萧大哥试试不就知道了
But you were in such a hurry to let Yan Yue burn them.
但你却急着让偃月烧掉
Actually, you just
其实是你自己
don't want him to compete.
不想让萧大哥上战场
Since you sent someone to watch me,
你既然派人监视我
you know very well
那我究竟有没有答应我阿父
whether I promised my father
破坏你的比试
to sabotage your competition.
你也心知肚明
Why did you put such a big blame on me?
何必给我扣这么一大口黑锅
Why didn't you agree with your father?
你为何不答应你阿父破坏比试
His words seemed like a deal,
你阿父的话看似交易
but were actually a threat.
实则威胁
If you don't do as he asks,
你若不按照你阿父的要求去做
Li Lejun might really be pushed into a political marriage
李乐君或许真的会被世家
by the noble families.
推去和亲
And Yizhi won't be able to leave.
易之也就走不了了
Aren't you afraid?
难道你不怕吗
There are other ways to stop the political marriage.
阻止和亲还有别的办法
But I will not trade three provinces and their people for it,
但我不会拿三州国土和百姓去换
nor will I sacrifice the honor of the Beifu soldiers.
更不会拿北府将士的荣誉去换
Xiao Wuyi, don't look down on me.
萧无衣 你别小看我
As for you, Xiao Wuyi,
倒是你萧无衣
you just
其实是你
don't want Yao to compete, right?
不想让萧大哥上战场吧
You are afraid his military merits will surpass yours
你是怕他军功胜过你
and steal your thunder.
抢了你的风头
I heard your horseback archery
我听说你的骑射技术
were taught by him.
还是他教的呢
Xie Jiayu, don't provoke me.
谢嘉鱼 少激我
If you really want to leave Jingan Mansion
你若真的还想全须全尾地
in one piece
离开靖安王府
and live the carefree life you and Yizhi dream of,
去过你和易之梦中的逍遥日子
mind your own business
就少管我萧家的闲事
and stay away from me.
离我远一点
Otherwise, I'm not sure if I...
否则我也不确定我还
I can let you leave alive.
还能否让你活着离开
You should be glad
你应该感到庆幸
that I don't want to lose my best friend.
我还不想失去我最好的朋友
Scared?
怕了吗
You should be.
怕就对了
My Lady.
女郎
Are you okay?
你没事吧
Did His Highness bully you?
世子没欺负你吧
It was just helping Yao out.
不就是帮萧大哥一个忙吗
Why was he acting like that?
怎的如此凶
Before the competition,
比试之前
Xie Jiayu is not allowed to set a single foot out of Wensheng Courtyard.
不许谢嘉鱼离开闻笙苑半步
Xiao Wuyi.
萧无衣
Anmin?
大哥
Did you ground Xie Jiayu
你禁足谢嘉鱼
because she helped me improve the stirrups and saddles?
是因为她帮我改进了马镫马鞍吗
You worry too much.
大哥多虑了
Xie Jiayu is from a noble family.
谢嘉鱼是世家出身
I was afraid she would ruin the competition
我怕她破坏比赛
and ruin the Beifu Army's reputation.
毁我北府声名
Nonsense.
胡说
When I suspected her,
我当时怀疑她的时候
you believed her.
你就相信她
Now I am willing to believe her.
现如今我愿意相信她了
Yet you're suspecting her because she's from a noble family?
你说你怀疑她世家出身
You simply want to use Xie Jiayu as an example
你无非是想用谢嘉鱼
to show everyone
做给所有人看
that absolutely no one is allowed
决不允许有任何人
to help me get a spot in the competition.
帮我争取比试名额
You have prepared for the Beifu Army's reform for so long,
北府改制你准备了这么久
but you never told me a word about it.
也从未与我透露过半句
In your eyes,
在你眼里
am I just a piece of trash
你大哥我是不是就是
that the Beifu Army doesn't want?
你北府不愿意收的废物
Lock this place up.
把这里锁上吧
I'm going out for a walk.
我出去走走
Don't follow me.
不必跟了
Why won't you let me compete?
你凭什么不让我上场
I don't accept this!
我不服
In your eyes,
在你眼里
am I just a piece of trash
你大哥我是不是就是
that the Beifu Army doesn't want?
你北府不愿收的废物
Anmin!
大哥
♪ We only live for what we can't let go ♪
哥
Yao.
尧儿
It's fine.
没事的 没事
Don't scare me.
你不要吓唬娘
Anmin!
哥
What are you doing here?
你来干什么
Are you here to see if my son is dead?
你来看我的儿子死了没有是不是
Darling.
夫人
You Lis
你们姓李的
took the life of one of my sons,
夺走我一个儿子的命还不够
yet you're still living under his name.
还用他的名字在活
Now, do you want the life of my other son, too?
你还想要我另外这个儿子的命吗
Father.
父亲
Who am I?
我是谁
When the Phoenix Heart Token appears, peace shall be restored in the world.
雀骨出 天下定
Your Highness.
太子殿下
♪ No need to speak, just leave it all to fate ♪
您是先帝和先皇后之子
You are the true heir of Ye.
您才是我大邺正统
Now, the remaining Shadow Envoys
今 尚存影使
are willing to follow you
愿跟随太子
to restore order,
拨乱反正
reclaim the throne,
夺回大统
trample Northern Qin,
踏平北秦
and return to the old capital!
还于故都
Father.
父亲
♪ What's right or wrong is better left unsaid ♪
臣萧驹
am willing to follow you, Your Highness.
愿追随太子
It's so late.
这么晚了
Why isn't Wuyi back yet?
无衣怎么还不回来呀
Judging by the noise,
听这动静
he must still be at the racecourse.
应该还在马场呢
In Jiuzhang Plain,
他在九丈原
he suffered life-threatening injuries.
受的可是九死一生的重伤啊
He can't afford to exhaust himself like this.
这可折腾不起啊
Darling.
夫人哪
How long are you going to punish Wuyi?
你还要惩罚无衣到什么时候啊
I didn't punish him.
我没有惩罚他
But don't you think you two
但你不觉得你们俩之间
are too polite
太过客气
and distant with each other?
太过陌生了吗
You are closer to Yuanji, to Ruisheng,
你对元姬 对蕊生
and even to that newlywed from the Xie family
甚至对那个刚过门的谢家丫头
than you are to Wuyi.
都比对无衣更亲近些
When Wuyi came back injured,
无衣受伤回来
did you even ask about his injuries?
你有问过他伤势一句吗
I know.
我知道
It's about Sheng.
阿晟的事
But Wuyi was just a baby then.
但那时无衣尚在襁褓
If you want to blame someone, blame me.
你要怪的话 该怪我呀
I don't blame him.
我没有怪他
Ever since he found out who he really was,
是他自己知道自己是谁以后
he has been fighting at the border
一直在边境打仗
and refused to come back.
不愿意回来
That's because he is afraid you'll be sad to see him.
那是孩子怕你见到他会伤心
And Anmin,
还有安民
he still doesn't know
他至今都不知道
that it's you who doesn't want him to return to the Northern Border
是你不愿他再回北境
and on the battlefield again.
是你不愿他再上战场
So he has taken all his resentment over the years
所以他就把这些年所有的怨气
out on Wuyi.
都冲着无衣去了
Fortunately, they are both tough on the outside but warm on the inside.
幸而两个孩子面冷心热
But if this misunderstanding continues,
但若再这么误会下去
it will sooner or later turn into real animosity.
早晚会弄假成真的
Darling,
夫人哪
do you really want to see
你难道真的想看到
the two brothers at odds with each other?
他们两兄弟不和吗
Anmin wants to return to the Northern Border.
大哥想回北境
That's good.
也好
Currently, the Beifu camps are still short of organization.
如今北府各营建制尚缺
He has the talent to lead troops.
大哥有领兵之才
If he is willing to return,
若他愿意回来
your pressure on the western front next year will be lessened.
明年西线上您的压力也小些
You are absolutely right.
你说得太对了
Quickly write to your mother and tell Anmin to return to the battlefield.
快写信给阿母 让安民回战场
Young Master Yao.
大公子
Don't help me.
不用扶
Stop practicing.
你不要再练了
Your leg can't take this kind of torment.
你的腿经不起这样的折腾
Do you also think I'm useless?
难道连你也看我不中用吗
Even though I can't ride a horse,
我虽然不能骑马
my archery
但我的箭术
and close combat skills
我近身搏斗的功夫
are no worse than Xiao Wuyi's.
一点都不比萧无衣差
He learned wrestling from me back then.
当年他的摔跤还是跟我学的
On what grounds does he stop me from competing?
他凭什么不让我上场
I'm worried about your legs.
我是担心你的腿
My father doesn't care about me.
我父亲不在乎我
My younger brother looks down on me.
我弟弟看不起我
Do you also...
难道连你也
Prepare more medicine for bruises and injuries for Young Master Yao.
给大公子多备些跌打损伤的药
Yes.
诺
Nanxing.
南星
Don't you think this room is very stuffy?
你不觉得这个屋子很闷吗
It's like a prison.
像一座监牢
It's only been two days,
这才两日
and you can't stay still anymore.
女郎就待不住了
Just like at home before,
跟从前在家里一样
you always want to run outside.
总想着往外跑
Her Highness couldn't control you.
郡主管都管不了
If this is a prison,
这要是监牢
it's the most wonderful prison in the world.
那可就是天底下最美妙的监牢喽
These are the recent requests on Miraculous Craft.
这是这几日在妙手登记求购的
Take a look
女郎看看
and see if there are any mechanical gadgets
有没有哪些机关巧物
that you're interested.
是您有想法的
You can make some to pass the time.
做一两个打发打发时间
The competition is in a few days.
过几日就比试了
It will pass.
熬一熬也就过去了
A wooden kite that can carry a person and fly.
能驮着人飞的木鸢
An arrow that bends its path to pursue prey.
追着猎物拐弯的箭
Fire oil that cannot be extinguished by water.
水也扑不灭的火油
And the buyers' names...
这买者的名字
Red Dragon, Black Dragon,
红龙 黑龙
Black Dragon, Full Moon.
黑龙 圆月
Isn't it obvious they are Qing Long and Yan Yue?
这不明摆着青龙 偃月吗
This must be Xiao Wuyi sending them to make things difficult for me.
这定是萧无衣让他们来刁难我的
So boring.
好无聊啊
Someone!
来人啊 来人啊
Is anybody there?
有没有人啊
Let's go!
走
The fire thunderstone of the Beifu Army
这北府军的火雷
is truly all bark and no bite.
真是雷声大雨点小
I don't know who designed them.
也不知道是谁设计的
They just wasted my time.
白耽误我工夫
I have to use mine.
还得用我那个
I'm a genius.
不愧是我
Ghost!
鬼啊
Are you really Li Yunzhao's daughter?
你真是李云昭的女儿
You don't look much like her.
长得不大像啊
But you have some skills.
不过有点本事
I have to say,
别说 这引火雷啊
after you modified this fire thunderstone,
经过你这么一改造
its power actually increased quite a bit.
威力倒是大了不少
How much saltpeter did you use?
你用了多少硝石
Hey, who are you?
不是 你谁啊
Do I know you?
我认识你吗
Move. I'm going out.
让开 我要出门了
Wait a minute.
你等会儿
Xiao Wuyi really didn't lie to me.
这萧无衣啊 果然没骗我
You do have some talent.
你确实有点天赋
I'm definitely taking you
你这个徒弟啊
as my apprentice.
我收定了
Let me show you my fire thunderstone.
我让你看看我的引火雷
Its power is no less than yours.
威力啊 不比你的小
Let's exchange our thoughts on this.
咱俩交流交流心得
Who said I'm going to be your apprentice?
谁说要做你徒弟了
Are you drunk in broad daylight?
大白天的 喝醉了
Your temper is quite like your mother's.
脾气倒是跟你阿母挺像的
How could you possibly know my mother?
你怎么可能认识我阿母
Not only do I know her,
我不但认识 我
but we fought a lot when we were young.
年轻的时候我们没少打架
Let me tell you a secret.
我告诉你个秘密
Your mother doesn't have much time left.
你阿母她命不久矣
What did you say?
说谁命不久矣呢
Listen.
我告诉你
Don't use seniority to boss me around.
你少拿辈分压我
You designed this fire thunderstone?
这引火雷你设计的
The design is truly terrible.
设计得真差
What's wrong with it? Tell me.
哪儿差了 你说清楚
It's too big.
太大了
Do you know what "all bark and no bite" means?
知道什么叫作雷声大雨点小吗
What do you know?
你懂什么呀
Big?
大
Its power is huge!
它威力大呀
The ones I design, even if they are only this small,
我设计的 哪怕这么点大
are more powerful than yours.
也比你的威力大
Okay, okay.
好好好
W-We'll talk about this later.
我 我们回头再交流这个
Let me tell you.
我跟你说
I've never been wrong in fortune-telling.
我这个人算命从来没出过差错
Not only did I figure out that your mother doesn't have much time left,
我不仅算出你娘命不久矣
but I also figured out you will marry twice,
我还算出来你这辈子是二婚
no, three times in your life.
不 三婚的命
And your husband, he'll die young.
且你的夫君 他短命
Is that so?
是吗
Nanxing, get him!
南星 上
Who are you saying doesn't have much time left?
说谁命不久矣你
-Watch out for the fire thunderstone -Who are you cursing?
小心引火雷 咒谁啊你
Why are you glaring at me?
瞪我干什么
I told you to watch out for the fire thunderstone.
我都说了 小心火雷
Watch out for the fire thunderstone.
小心火雷
Qing Long, long time no see.
小青龙 好久不见
Did you miss me?
想我了吧
Give it back to me.
你还我
You know how to make stirrups, too?
你还会做马镫呢
At first glance,
我一看
I knew this was designed for Xiao Yao.
我就知道这是给萧尧设计的
Xiao Wuyi
萧无衣啊
asked me to design one before, too.
以前也让我设计过
My design
我那设计
was much better than this.
比这个强多了
You designed one for him, too?
你也给他设计过
When?
什么时候
A long time ago.
早了
It was probably right after Xiao Yao got injured.
应该是萧尧刚刚受伤的时候吧
Xiao Wuyi was worried his brother
萧无衣担心他大哥
couldn't get over his disability.
因为残疾的事情想不开
It was a pity.
可惜了
He told me to stop when the blueprint was only half done.
图纸画到一半 不让我做了
Why stop?
为何不做
Naturally, it's because someone
自然是有人
didn't want Xiao Yao to ride a horse onto the battlefield again.
不希望萧尧再骑马上战场呗
Kiddo.
丫头
You are quite talented
你这个黄白点金之术
in alchemy and metalworking,
颇有天赋
but your structural design still lacks a bit.
但是架构上还有些欠缺
It's my blueprint. You...
我的图纸你
Hold on.
别动
Look.
看
If it's connected like this,
如此连接
and then attached to the saddle,
再连接上马鞍
wouldn't it be much more flexible?
是不是会灵活很多
The biggest problem with your design
你这个设计啊
is that it's not flexible enough.
最大的问题就是不够灵活
It works fine with light pressure,
不用力还好
but once too much force is applied, it creates drag
一用力就容易产生拖拽
and can throw the rider off,
人就很容易从马上掉下来
leaving them vulnerable to being trampled by their own horse.
被自己的马踩死
Wait, wait, wait.
等等 等等 等等
Did you say applying force causes dragging?
你说用力会发生拖拽
Oh, no.
不好
His Highness is testing the stirrups for Young Master Yao.
世子正在为大公子试马镫
What?
什么
Why is it blurry again?
怎么又看不清了